okay so let's get started with today
lesson and let's see what Yan likes to
do research on alright so today we're
going to be talking about model
predictive policy learning with
uncertainty regularization for driving
in dense traffic what a mouthful the
nice part is that in roughly 50 minutes
you're going to be able to understand
every word in this title and you
actually should be able to even be ready
to implement this because we basically
know all the basic components that we
have cover so far and so this is just
you know put together something but how
perhaps not in a trivial way but but I
don't think it's too crazy so this is
work done by my friend and colleague me
Kyle enough myself and then Yong here at
grant a few years back I think it was
2019 so last year I think oh maybe the
year before I don't know all right
so let's see how you can learn how to
drive the model free reinforcement
learning way right so pay attention to
the car here in in the back this display
guy so let's say I'd like to train this
this guy with model free reinforcement
learning so how would you go about that
so you would have to try
um to do things that are maybe not good
and then if you hear uh shouldn't do
those things right because it's not good
and so you have to die a few times right
before actually learning not to die but
that's arguably not the way you learn
how to drive right especially if you're
driving your your parents car and you
don't really want to crash your parents
car before learning how to not crash
your parents car right so let's figure
out a more principled way to learn how
to drive a car right so I would argue
here and this is just you know my
intuition is that if you if you have a
car now you're driving a hundred
kilometers per hour which is like thirty
meters per second if you look 30 meters
in front of you that will mean that you
look one second in the future right and
therefore you can see that you know the
road center turns slightly to the left
in one second in the future therefore I
would like to change the steering wheel
right now such that in one second I will
be you know following the ended
trajectory and where the street takes me
to okay so here I'm just trying to you
know push forward the idea that we need
to look in the future in order to be
able to make you know some sort of nice
like you know plan of action right so
you'd like to figure out that if
something is not good you may not want
to do it so it's that you don't get into
trouble so but hmm was the main problem
here others other people are problem
right so here you have that you know the
eCos around you are quite not
deterministic therefore it might be
slightly hard to take an account every
possible thing that might happen right
so let me give you like an introduction
here or a small recap of the what are
the main components in this system here
so we have a agent here represented by
this pink brain which gets as input a
state s T and produces in action is an
output which is a T which is for example
my steering control and my acceleration
or braking signal moreover I observe a
cost which is you know a consequence of
taking a specific action a given that I
find myself in state s T ok so if I
should be okay let me see there are chat
messages here let me see what's going on
okay people are laughing cool alright on
the other side you had the real world
the real world given a internal state
you get a new action and then you
produce the new state ok and also you
produce what is the result this
consequence city to provide to your
agent and so this is how you know how
you can have like a network interacting
with a real world you take actions given
a specific state and the word give you
gives you the next state and the next
consequence so this is model free
because you interact with the real world
but then the nice part is that you can
do interaction with the model of the
world okay so under on the left hand
side instead of trying things in the
real world and you know try to cook and
you burn something and then that's not
good you burnt also your hand burn my
arm nasty making cookies maybe you would
like to try in your mind first how can I
make cookies without getting burnt maybe
don't touch the oven with your hands
right that would be very
smart option right all right so how how
can we get how can we think right how
can we ponder how can we make this kind
of interaction between my actions and
the expected consequences you know of
taking a specific action with actually
without actually taking the action right
so how can I avoid to burn myself again
tonight while baking without actually
getting burned right so you want to
think ahead
don't touch what's hot hmm okay all
right so how do we train this word model
the same way we trained it last week
right so we start with initial state we
provide some you know action which was
random last week and this week instead
is not for example the action here might
be the action taken by some expert that
we observed like mom cooking for you of
dead don't know and you can see what is
the the current state and then you can
have the next state dinner is ready
mmm I'm gonna gray I'm actually hungry
p.m. all right more or you also had the
consequence 15 they're going to be you
know your mouth is watering anyhow
you're gonna be providing now like a
distance between this state that are
observed in the real world in the state
that are provided to you by the model of
the world and then you have an MSc loss
right so that's just regression so you
try to regress what is the next state
given that you start from the initial
same state and you provide like specific
action okay so far this is something we
already seen last week just give you an
overview again right all right keep coin
if you don't complain so let's figure
out here what we can do for example in
my case in this case I don't have my
model out putting a cost or I don't have
the word out put in a cost and more
specifically I have that in my case
I will have my brain here my agent that
again takes a state and provides an
action which is feeding this model and
then I have my cost is going to be a
differentiable function of the state
okay which is exactly what we had seen
last week right with the final you know
destination to be you know the specific
thing that you gramm run back
propagation through time and back
propagation through time would be
unrolling this loop right so you go
forward you go like that and then you do
a back problem okay all right cool so
let me introduce to you right now the
data set right so far littles you know
just like setting up the problem so here
it's my actual real case scenario I have
six cameras seven cameras mounted on it
on the top of a 30-story building facing
the i-80 interstate segment on the of
the highway array and so here I have
these cameras recording these cars first
part is going to be fixing the
perspective right such that I can have
like a hovering view where I cat op down
view moreover here we extract some
bounding boxes for each baked-on right
so there is detection there is
regression of the you know well
detection and figuring out the size of
this bounding boxes and then there is
tracking because these bounding boxes
are following my cars and so you can see
here the red track on the left hand side
or you can see like the the red pickup
car a pickup truck that is you know from
both views or from the top camera down
to one single view here I can input
these cars into my you know Python
program item game emulator game engine
and I can draw this representation in
this case you can still see the red
tractor the pickup pickup pickup truck
and then on the bus on the right hand
side so here for every each and every
vehicle the blue the cyan one I have two
vectors the vector PT which is
representing the position of the vehicle
the
we are part VT which is the velocity
which is you know vector representing
the VX and V Y component and then
moreover I given that I know what is the
kinematics of driving a car or a bicycle
I can invert the kinematics of these
cars that have been driven by you know
experts and I can figure out what the
actions are that you know what the
actions of the driver are in the sense
that if the car moves with a rectilinear
uniform motion you have no action right
so if you don't apply any acceleration
which is longitudinal or transverse you
have you know the car keeps going so if
you have a rectilinear uniform motion
there is no action every time you try to
diverge from this you know motion for
example to accelerate you break or you
steer then you have some basically you
know action involved right you can
invert the kinematic model in order to
figure out what the action is cool so
here again in this representation which
is the thing that I call machine
representation I have again the same
vehicle there the other pickup car and
one on the right hand side so in this
case each vehicle here has a bounding
box which is representing my viewable
area so each car can only view that kind
of box around itself and so for example
here I can extract the first box where
April replace myself in the centre and I
movie I move myself to the blue channel
again such that i'ma I'm not like I make
myself different from the others and the
red lane the red channel represents the
lane and the green channel represents
the others wake on other vehicles you
have the other guy here this one here
that one and the last one okay and here
you can see again the pickup pickup
truck there the red one and then here
you have a piece of the bus so these are
my images I T or
serve Asians right these are
representing two things the state of the
lanes of the street basically and the
second part is going to be they
represent the traffic situation
surrounding me
so overall the set of PT the position
within the velocity and I team this
observation represent my state s T so as
T represents the current state at a
specific time T right for my given
vehicle so far any question how is it
clear I mean we already seen basically
everything so far last week and I just
gave you like an overview about the
specific data sets so there are no new
concept so far so it should be clear
right yeah no okay you're very quiet
today
maybe it's my audio on okay you're not
texting so I expect you to be okay yes
it's clear okay thank you all right cool
so the cost right so we define before we
said before that my cost is going to be
a function of my state so let's see how
I compute this cost there are two
different costs there is a lane cost
that is basically telling me whether I
am on the lane like within the lane on
like inside the lane or I am going off
lane off road and the other one is going
to be a cost that is gonna be telling me
how close I am to other vehicles so the
first one it looks like this on my
y-axis so the x-axis the direction of
motion y-axis is gonna be the one that
is you know 90 degrees to the left in
their form you can think about having a
potential it is like a house on top of
you if you overlay this with the red
channel there is some intersection on
the left hand side this intersection the
height of that intersection will go to
zero if you are exactly in the center of
the two lanes if you are shifted the
words one side you're gonna get you know
some nonzero intersection and if you're
exactly on top of the lane you get is
actually the
on the on the on the top of this
triangle right on the other side you
have the proximity cost so I have
exactly the same but for the other
vehicles night so in this case I have
one longitudinal sorry transverse
potential I have one longitudinal
potential which is changing the length
with the speed so the faster I go and
the more I would like to look ahead and
behind in this case in in the slower I
go I can you know I don't really care so
much about things that too far I just
look close to myself so we could plug
these two things in my environment you
can see now that there is an
intersection for example here that is
pretty high for the purple because we
are exactly in front of in front of us
but then the orange is quite low because
it's you know further away in the front
so you can simply do the multiplication
of the two you can get what is my
current proximity cost okay so how does
this look right now I can show you for
example for a situation where we go at
20 kilometers per hour you have all
these vehicles are very close to each
other and then if you go at 50
kilometers per hour you know on average
every one is a bit further away so if
you multiply that potential that is in
the Y and the other one that was in the
X you get something that looks like this
okay and in the case that we go at a
higher speed you cannot get something
like this because I gain the extension
in the X direction depends on the speed
and you can tell like that is the right
one is further far reaching front and
back cool so how do we get this final
cost well my final cost right now at
least as we what we establish this paper
we just multiplied this potential mask
with the green channel and then we pick
the max basically we figure out which
one is the closest car or close the same
the the part closest to us belongs to
some other object and so if you multiply
element wise multiply
these two guys and then you take the max
you get a number and the cool part is
that differentiable right so now you can
run gradients through on the network
such that you know you can compute some
actions such that that value overall is
going to be reduced and it goes to zero
such that you avoid collisions all right
so let me give you now the outline of
the talk of the lesson for today so
first we said we had to learn how to
mimic the word rain so that was pretty
abstract so far now we can start getting
concrete you know tools and information
so first we want to learn and mimic the
real world second part we'd like to use
the you know the learned model of the
environment in order to train this agent
by you know making thinking how to drive
so first you learn how other vehicles
behave in the real world second part
given that you have an understanding of
how other people interact you try to
think what would happen if I you know
perform such an such action in this in
this condition finally we can figure out
what is a nice way to evaluate a
possible way to evaluate this policy
back in the real world right so once
you've thought how to drive let's figure
out whether you can drive cool so let's
get started with the first part the
world model predicting what's next given
history and action so this is gonna be
something that you already had seen a
few lessons back but let me give you
again like a full picture here so we
have a world model which is fed with my
s1 to T which is a sequence of States
and each state represent is represented
by a position vector P T a velocity
vector in V T and these context images I
T these observations so this is a set of
things of course as you can tell you
will have different you know in
different input branches in your net
right because
there are different kind of data one is
you know four-dimensional vector the
other is an image you'd like to use a
convolutional net moreover this word
modern gets an action and the word model
will produce a prediction for the next
action on the other side you had the
real word which is telling you well
these happen instead okay so that's a
target okay so how do we train this
stuff as we said it's just a regression
problem so we just train with MSE right
so we have my state like a sequence of
state an action we provide this to this
predictor module the predictor gives me
some kind of hidden representation of
the you know of whatever future then I
have a decoder which is decoding this
hidden representation of the future and
this one this one should give me a
prediction right so this is pretty
straightforward right you have a
predictor that predicts the past into
the hidden representation of the future
they have a decoder which is decoding
into the actual future so we have a
target on the other side so all you need
to do is going to be having this tool
going inside an MSc then you minimize
the MSE by training these two modules so
does it work what's the action here so
the action here is for example the
acceleration and the steering steering
command that the we have observed in our
data set right so my state's s1 to t are
a sequence of you know observations of
position velocities and context images
in the action are the action taken by
the driver that I obtained by inverting
the kinematic model of the car PT is the
position of the car and VT is the
velocity of the car so a position
velocity in the 80 is the acceleration
right so PT x and y position VT x and y
velocity 80 x and y
acceleration basically is it preferred
to add the decoder instead simply using
a predictor to improve the accuracy so
the predictor predicts what's gonna be
the hidden state of the future okay so
the predictor gets the past and compress
it and tries to give you what is the
future you know the future hidden
representation then you have this code
you'd like to decode it right this is
just you know one neural net but we'd
like to separate those into blocks okay
so the action at eighty is calculated
from st plus one
yeah so these actions are the ground
truth action coming from the yeah from
the ground truth thanks how do we
calculate st we don't how do we get
actual sto
the actual str i show you before right
the the camera are checking the the cars
going on the highway i get the bounding
boxes i track the bounding boxes and
therefore i have all those you know
positions x and y's over time and then
those are DX the PT positions you can
also compute the velocity right you know
position time t plus 1 minus position at
times T divided by time you have the
velocity wait I'm still a little
confused on the role of the decoder is
it just converting the vector
representation of the future from the
predictor into actual real-world
predictions yeah that's correct
so the decoder is just like semantic the
subdivision right now it's just one
neural net and you can think about the
neural net has having an encoder and
decoder all the time right you can
decide where you want to have the hidden
representation how do we hold on how do
we determine the dimensionality of a
spread output well it depends on your
network right so whatever your network
is outputting in my case I think it 128
dimensional
vector foresty since there are variable
number of cars surrounding our agent
vehicle then okay that's a good question
is the size of SD viable so st
represents the position and velocity of
myself and then i have an image
which shows me the occupancy grid
basically shows me what the surrounding
right so I show you here this is my
image IT which represents the
configuration of the lanes of the street
and what is the configuration of the
vehicles you have not different number
of vehicles other weight vehicles in the
left image and the right image
nevertheless an image can just show your
any number of vehicles right so that's
very cute way of using images just for
the fact that I don't need to have a
variable length set of you know things
right otherwise you should have used
some kind of you know attention or asset
network or some other you know crafty
things this one you know you can use
images is a mean of representing
information these are not natural images
right these are completely synthetic
images but I can use them in order to
cope with the fact that I have a
different number of items nearby me yeah
I think I answer everyone
yeah that's a boolean green yeah yeah it
is a boolean grid right so my image has
RGB and each of them are or 0 or 1 in
this case they are I you can see the
pixels and they are a little bit blurry
because there is like I think some up
sampling with by linear by linear up
sampling here in this case let me think
yeah I think there is something like
that maybe I should be a boolean grid
that's correct I think here we do okay
there is down sampling this there is
down sampling so these images actually
are larger in there are binary but then
there are too large so it's so that we
actually make them forth and by doing
the fourth you know scaling down they
start looking like a little blurring
right now otherwise if you have a car
that turns you're gonna have all that
kind of staircase right right now
instead if you have this kind of blurred
version it's no like that stir-crazy
okay too many questions with with a
differentiable cost function do we back
propagate from the end of the trajectory
all the way back yeah it's gonna be yeah
sure that's correct we are gonna see
this in the second part right this is
first part where I train a regression
network so here it was the first model
right so you have like a encoder decoder
which is not because it's a predictor
predictor decoder just from because of
the fact that the amount stuff on the
left hand side is from the past right
that's why you need a predictor that
gives you the next thing in line but
otherwise you can think about an encoder
but it's not correct way of thinking
just you know similar
does it work so on the left hand side
you have the actual future the thing
that really happened on the right hand
side you get the deterministic you know
predictor decoder and the network that I
just show you train with MSC in order to
replicate the thing on the left this is
from the testing set of course and it's
been trained on the training set so on
the top right you're gonna see the
frames you're gonna have a 10 frame per
second and the direction of motion is
going forward and the blue guy is our
self the green guys are the others and
the red are the lanes so you can see
here that after 3 seconds for 5 seconds
everything gets quite [ __ ] up yep
nothing works
ok how nice I just taught you something
that doesn't work how happy are you are
you happy
no I can't hear you but okay I mean yeah
thank you for the no the not happy okay
alright so what's happening okay who can
tell them you should know right what's
happening because Jana has been talking
about this stuff all along this past
three weeks so what's the problem here
latent variables your cadet the solution
what's the problem okay
the MSE loss yeah I was the actual
problem oh okay someone answer is
someone answer LM whose LM I don't know
its average in future outcomes yeah yes
yes is someone answer stop okay this is
basically everything that can happen
from that initial point in time you know
you have everything else therefore it
looks like that you know every kind of
image looks up like a blur the image
right so again you had this example from
yan if you have a pencil on on a plane
and I since I can't really draw in 3d
I'm gonna give you the top-down view on
the right-hand side let's say you make
it falling right one two three four
times five six whatever and if you
compute what is the average right
folding location well this is since is a
you know X&Y is just you know coordinate
the average final location is like oh
the pen never fed and it's really wrong
right otherwise if you actually use a
pixel space you would have like the
overlay anyhow the problem is this one
right you have a multi possible future
and then you only try to regress the
average teacher right how do we fix it I
really told me we latent variable the
ACS no no no no I want latent variable
latent variable this is okay cool this
is the the energy base stuff he likes a
lot and we like it all right because we
like young
so okay and actually you already know
everything here so this is the original
Network I just show you before it
doesn't work and let's fix this so in
the center we're going to be summing
something and with some this
low-dimensional latent variable in green
ZT which goes through a you know
expansion expansion module such that he
fixed the image the dimensionality so
where's this ZT coming from well I guess
you can tell so that T is going to be
chosen such that the prediction is
minimized you know that the MSE is
minimized for this specific peak of the
prediction right so you can do inference
right so you train everything it's a
real train actually because we trained a
deterministic one now you can do
inference of the latent variable such
that you can still get the MSE to zero
by doing gradient descent into latent
space right so you can change that set
into two to chain chain chain chain
chain until the emissive dies
this is very expensive because you have
two degrees in the same thing to the
damn thing there otherwise you can just
plug this you know you can actually
predict that latent how do you do that
with an encoder and there you go where
did the encoder is so the encoder gets
the future state and gives you the mean
and variance from which you sample the
what is it Irish variational predictive
network actually is a variational
conditional predictive network because
you actually start from a actual action
89 so 80 is the condition is it
advisable to help the output fed into a
encoder for the latent variable during
training oh never mind okay all right
yeah that's that's how yeah okay that
was the answer yeah so you don't have to
all right this is just a very convenient
way to get that said T I guess in the
next next lab when we do the energy
based model we're going to do first
inference right but inference is not
take you forever because every time you
have to try try try try try try a new
Zed then where you start with why is
there an arrow from St plus 1 to F Inc
because unless you know what will happen
how will you find that ZT right so that
Z T is the missing information that you
can't have from the past because
something happened you know now my
roommate is gonna be coming naked inside
oh okay now it doesn't do that things
you know that's unpredictable part and
may never happen before yeah hopefully
likely okay the point was that given
that I have no idea about what's gonna
happen next in the future you know a
meteorite crashes here you can't really
predict the unpredictable unpredictable
part right you don't know what's going
on
therefore during training I look in the
future what's happening huh I see
something as I get information from the
future and from that information I can
predict the latent variable okay so
someone's gonna say oh you're cheating
right because you look in the future and
you don't have the future at testing
time right when you drive you don't have
access to the future but since your
training here you can kind of cheat and
look look what's happened there but we
can fix this how do we fix that so this
is the posterior blind of a variational
encoder and you fix it this way right
you enforce the posterior the decoder
they saw the encoder there to be giving
you a distribution that is as close as
possible to the prior to that K ed right
and so in this case you learn how to
predict basically mean meaningful latent
variable ZT trying to you know
disconnect as well from that kind of
future okay I'm not sure what Allah is
it
I'm not I'm not really understanding the
f X part FX means a expansion so that T
is the latent might be you know 16
dimensional vector very tiny thing and
the F bread must can easily be like some
kind of spatial information right so
given that is the state is an image are
gonna be like you know throughout New
York neural-net I'm gonna be making it
convolutional nets a bit smaller it's
gonna be still spatial I won't be
collapsing in one vector such that my X
FX be explained expander will expand my
16 dimensional vector may be in two
sixteenth lanes of the same size of this
F pred hidden representation okay such
that I can sum them together could you
repeat how you're putting the
restriction on the model not being able
to look at actually interstates so right
now only by looking in the future you
can figure out what's happening okay so
this F encoder is trained to produce the
latent variable which is minimizing that
MSC so that's not the variational at
encoder encoder there on the top part
yeah it's gonna be trying to predict the
latent that really gives you you know
zero prediction error but then on the
other side you also enforce that encoder
to give you something that is close to a
normal to to the prior feed over there
so the fact that there is like a KL term
between the posterior and the Q and the
P allows you later on to sample from the
prior when you are actually doing you
know you're using this network see you
build a prior distribution and then
during into the viewing test time
instead of looking at the actual future
state you sample from the distribution
label you just learn you just assemble
from the prior distribution so this is
going to be a fixed prior you fix the
prior which is a normal distribution
even forced the encoder you know to
stick with this kind of prior or you can
even learn what is the distribution of
those latent variables you can do many
things this is what actually we managed
to to get better
best result with okay look do you
enforce the encoder to give you
something that looks like a prior which
is a Gaussian you know independent
Gaussian and then from independent in
also I saw what's called I saw something
I forgot that you know the unitary
identity matrix right for the covariance
and so later on we are gonna be just
sampling from that prior distribution to
get late into that to look you know
reasonable okay thanks sure okay there
are many more questions how do the
latent variable prevent the averaging oh
well that's actually so basically
whenever okay
so let's say we train the brains on the
bottom the deterministic part right so
at the end you're gonna get a prediction
for the you know predicted state for the
future state which is looking like some
kind of possible but you know average
future now for a specific future you can
figure out now you know by doing
gradient descent you can minimize that
MSE by changing that additional latent
variable this is how latent variable
models work right so for every training
sample you have one latent variable
which is gonna give you exactly zero and
the seed loss you can train first with
all of them such that you can get a very
initial starting point which is the
average prediction and then you can
refine that average average prediction
by adding this additional latent
variable and that value for the latent
variable can be found for example by
doing gradient descent meaning you
minimize the MSE like you minimize this
MSE loss by getting gradients coming
down here the gradient comes here and
then you get gradients here so you can
do that equal you know exact gets Z
minus ETA gradient of the loss with
respect to to the Z right got it okay
awesome
no that wasn't someone else saying got
it okay
someone had a question before okay I
don't know oh no it was the answer I
gave so basically we are adding the F
bread
f bread our prediction of what will
happen with FX the representation of the
what actually happens now FX is not what
actually happens if X is what I couldn't
figure out that would have happened
okay so f pred output it's what I I can
you know I would guess you know my best
prediction for what happens tomorrow is
going to be that the Sun will rise might
not be the case so the the Zed that
comes down to the F expander will add
that component that will you know manage
to fix my broken prediction right so the
lower branch will try to do as the best
job it can without having knowledge of
the future and the other one allows me
to refine my prediction to be actually
correct okay but in this case we have
access to the actual future so it's kind
of cheating nevertheless you enforce
that this generation of latent variable
is going to be as close as possible to
my prior distribution
I hope it makes more sense but maybe we
can go further and then you may get a
little bit clearer clear mind well last
question is Syd Garon okay starting to
make sense answer is it guaranteed that
there exists a Zed which gives us M s is
zero I think I'm not sure about
guarantees but if your network is
reasonably well behaved I guess yeah
you're guaranteed you know if your
network capacity is can over fit but you
can't over fit because you know there
are noise in the data you can reduce you
can zero out that noise by adding this
additional term so it's guaranteed if
the network is properly sized yeah okay
cool so inference how do we drive okay
we already spoiled okay more question
training time we try to learn qz4 that
close to prior petesy test time okay
yeah I'm getting there hold on all right
test time not test driving time right
how do the hell do you use this stuff
variation of predicted condition and
predicted net for inference cool so we
had this lower branch in this lower
dimensional latent variable not a no
sixteen dimensional vector and where it
comes from we sample from prior right
because we enforce that the encoder
there was trying to you know shoot it
towards this distribution hmm cool then
what do you do next you get the
prediction you put it back so you do a
outer aggressive step right you get next
prediction network next
yeah correct okay no one wrote anything
but I know you understood and so you
keep feeding this stuff does it work yes
it works so here you can see again a
comparison between the actual future on
the left hand side the deterministic
branch that is just just the lower
branch strain as before and then here I
give you four different draws from an
art and from a end distribution was
called I can I can tell the help normal
distribution so you have you know 200
times 4 so we have 800 samples from a
normal distribution of size I don't know
16 and I feed you know on the first 200
values to the first model then I start
again from from same past and I feed to
new 100 no no 200 200 new values today
to the Leighton there then I have third
time I get the same initial condition
and then I feed this sequence another
third sequence of 200 variables pay
attention here to the car on the
right-hand side of me that isn't a
circle white circle and then the guy
behind that guy right in this square
okay and so if you show if you see here
you get basically that all these
different predictions will predict a
different location for the car going
there the dead one in the circle and a
car behind the one one in the square
also has completely no arbitrary
prediction so this super cool right
right now you have that each of these
you know possible futures you know are
completely elucidated by my network so
this stuff doesn't exist
but we have a network that generates
future how cool is this right so before
maybe we had you know limited amount of
training data now we have a network that
is just generating futures from the Hut
like a magician right so this is super
super super cool you have infinite
amount of data which is you know
completely different from what actually
happened the actual future this data
comes from only observational data so
that we
have seen in the actual reality but is
applied to this specific initial
condition so what next now you can use
this huge amount of data to train this
policy right this network that allows
you to control our agent such that it
minimizes losses the loss that the cost
for the going over these lanes and the
cost for you know colliding against
other vehicles okay
the cool part is that okay I can tell
the design I should yeah I can tell you
the cool part is that this future here
these multiple futures come from the
specific sequence of latent variable you
feed to this network right
what if you perform gradient ascent in
the latent space you get your initial
you know sample from this normal
distribution then you tweak these values
such that you [ __ ] up the hardness
like you increase the hardness you don't
[ __ ] up you increase the hardness I like
to swear you know but you increase the
hardness for example you try to increase
the proximity cost right so you get the
sequence of latent where other cars are
gonna be like kamikaze like they are
gonna be driving into you and like crazy
so that's the super cool you have a
network that gives you futures that you
want right okay I'm already too excited
I will not be able to sleep tonight
okay question if we try to sample that
from Pisa during test time it is
possible for us to look for a specific
future for example I would like to know
the solution of turning left not moving
forward so here here I don't let me
think
right right so this predictive network
you feed the action right so this is a
condition a predictive network so we
have the action here on the bottom part
so you actually display the whole point
you can take different actions and the
whole future will change based on the
action you take right I was mentioning
here we have a initial state that's you
know the initial condition and then
given different latent you're gonna have
different kind of behavior of the other
vehicles and then you can decide to
tweak this latent by for example doing
gradient ascend in the latest pace by
increasing that kind of collision term
such that you have in our crazy cars
coming at you but nevertheless as you
pointed out here you can also figure out
what are the outcomes of changing the
action right that's exactly how we're
going to be training our policy that is
actually the whole thing right okay
issues first issue so given given that
you actually have access to the future
if you turn slightly to the left
everything is gonna turn to the right
right because if you drive you know you
turn to the left and how's gonna be like
like that right so if I turn to the left
you just turn to the right and turning
to the right is gonna be contributing in
a huge way to the MSC right so right now
you can I get basically that these MSC
lofts can be minimized if you were
encoder and they're in the latent
variable is gonna tell my bottom part
that everything is turned to turn to the
right but this is absolutely not what we
want right because we know how to tell
everything turns to the right because
that's deterministic right given the
past given that I turned to the left the
steering wheel everything turns to the
right I don't care I don't want to look
in the future to see everything turns to
the right regardless of what I'm doing
with my steering wheel right so this
it's a very very huge terrible problem
because the network basically was
learning to cheat right and was figuring
out that we were turning
without us telling the system we turned
so that was terrible because basically
this big arrow here is a leak of
information and therefore it was not any
more sensitive to the current action I
was providing to my predictor right this
was a very nice big nightmare how do you
now
kill that big arrow right so how do I
get my predictive network to actually
care about the action I take so let me
show you the EDD problem here so here we
have the real sequence of latent the one
that I actually have computed from in
minimizing the MSE yeah that the answer
that's correct so here I have the real
sequence of latent and the real sequence
of actions that are taken by the DEA
agent
and so here you can see is actually
speed up for time such that you can see
there is some kind of you know you know
turning then you can see here random
variables but the real sequence of
action you can see now that things are
kind of turning right you can see see
things are turning on the left on the
last one there you have the real
sequence of latent but simple actions
and
you can clearly see the last pile at the
last point that the turning came from
the mostly from the latent right so the
latent burial 1/10 encodes the rotation
in the action that it's written a tilde
and those are same sample at random
right so well symbol from other from
other episodes so the problem here is
that the fact that we were turning can
we learn
so you'd like to learn that thing you
would like to reject the fact that we
were turning right so the fact that the
thing turns should be completely
explainable by the action right and I
think yeah I don't know anyhow let me
show you how we fix the problem
sorry explain again it was very unclear
when you were saying first and last what
you were referring to okay I try again
so here we have four different
rectangles right in the the last one on
the right hand side you have the real
sequence of latent variable which are
this the latent variable that allows me
to get the precise the correct future
right so those are the latent variable
coming from the and from the encoder in
the variational encoder and have a have
the real sequence of actions taken by
the expert okay
the further the two blue the one that
have this blue here and this one here
are you know simple simple latent
variable that the till that means they
are sample so they are randomly sample
but I have the real sequence of actions
and so I would expect to see the
steering and the last one on the left
hand side I have the real sequence of
latent but then I have you know
arbitrary actions and so if I show you
again the animation you're gonna see
here there is you know some amount of
steering involved okay and you know the
steering comes from the actions then on
the other two examples here I show you
that the same actions are not providing
the same amount of steering now that I
had sample different latent variables
nevertheless if I use the you know exact
same latent variable all the steering
happens because of the latent variable
so my decoder will tell me if in my
network that things were turning just
because they have been encoded in the
latent variable rather than in the
action
all I can I think I was clear clear but
let me show you how we fix this
maybe oh is it is it clear what I'm
trying to show you yeah that was much
better so okay thank you see
but repeating we say repetitive and it's
in Latin repetition helps that's why you
had to practice practice practice okay
how do you fix the problem the problem
is that we have a not a memory leak but
information leak right the information
leaks from the from the future well it's
a bit late all right so how do we fix
this problem we fix this problem by
simply dropping out this latent and
picking it and sampling from the prior
distribution at random okay so we don't
always rely on the output of the
posterior network the encoder but
sometimes we pick from the posterior
from the prior in this way you can't
encode the rotation anymore in the
latent variable because sometimes it
will be missing and therefore the
network will be having to you know
exploit the action you provide so in
this case the purple on the right hand
side I show you two different sets of
latent variable but the real actions
okay and this network has been trained
with this dropout trick in so in this
case you can see that the rotation is
actually encoded by the action and no
longer by the latent variables as it was
the case before so we fix this problem I
think I should be speeding slightly a
little because we're kind of running way
too late so sorry I didn't know sit
notice
but okay what how do we train the agent
well this is pretty much what I said
before on the right hand side we learned
so far the the model of the world from
the real world on the left hand side
you're gonna be training this agent
through using this predictive model so
we have the agent which picks a initial
state the initial condition right
position velocity in those context
images and gives you a control an action
which is the acceleration in the
longitudinal direction and the
acceleration in the transverse direction
alright so how does it work so this is
how we train we have a state we feed a
state to the policy you get an action
then you feed both of them to the world
model right what does the model tell you
well you need to provide some you know
latent variable we also some possible
way that the future can you know evolve
then you get a prediction cool you feed
a prediction to these laws where the
lost is gonna be my cost of the task I'm
trying to accomplish in my case is gonna
be the summation of the proximity cost
the one that is telling me how close I
am to other vehicles plus some kind of
you know cost associated to the beam in
the center of the lane cool so in the
next state I I send it to the network
then the policy I get the next action I
feed both of them to the world model you
get the latent variable you get a new
prediction you send this to the loss and
more prediction like policy world model
latent variable next guy loss and finish
you do a back propagation to train the
policy model and doesn't work [ __ ]
what happened so we are basically
falling outside a manifold the policy
manages to you know crank up those
actions and give predictions that are
all black and all black is good because
zero cost right so that's bad okay so
here we actually went outside the road
and here we actually collided in two
other vehicles so let's maybe try to
imitate other vehicles so how do you do
that well you can say that the loss is
gonna be you know the task that we were
trying to accomplish plus some you know
regularizer which is you know expert
regularizer
what is this stuff so here you try also
to get the prediction by you know that
you would get by taking a specific
action as close as possible to the
action the actual future so you do that
for everyone but in this case you
actually have to kind of remove this
latent variable because the latent
variable gives you a specific prediction
it works better if you just work with
the average prediction we trained
evaluation of the encoder to just remove
it hmm does it work actually yeah
imitating the expert work so this is
kind of imitation learning but imitation
learning with you know model day so I
mean model basing imitation learning you
use your brain in order to try to
imitate others all right can we do
better yes we can do better and that's
going to be the end of the class so how
can we add a different kind of manifold
attractor what am I talking about here
so forward model uncertainty so my
predictive model outputs a prediction
given you know a state and the action
and then I have my cost here so this is
for example my cost the point is that
you know there are
always this cost can go whenever you're
outside the training region the one with
the red points right so if you are
within the red points as I show you in
the lab number three when we were doing
regression if you're within this
training region you have zero variance
right across those points is it go away
from those training region the variance
increases right guess what the variance
is differentiable let's run within
descent so we can try to run gradient
descent over the variance and yeah so
you minimize the variance by using SGD
so this is my uncertainty regularizer
so I have my predicted my policy which
is feeding my you know action to the
world model you get this latent variable
here and you get a prediction also you
get the task cost here which is you know
the minimization of the lane and
proximity cost yep in there you actually
can get several models or you can use
some the drop out trick we haven't
talked about but you can leave the drop
out on during inference such that you
can have multiple predictions and now
you can compute the variance
right of these predictions and you
multiply by a thing whatever a lambda
scaler and then my model uncertainty
regularizer leave some of the two and
you get the final loss to optimize and
that's it so that's the whole model
where the final loss is going to be my
DC task
plus this uncertainty this slides are
going to be in the next slide I give you
the links so in this one I show you in
pink that they actually managed to learn
how to drive by minimizing the
uncertainty of the predictive model so
the action takes an taken by the policy
are minimizing the uncertainty with
which the predictive network makes
predictions right what a mouthful but it
works very well and evaluation I'll show
you just very quickly here in the yellow
is the original car and the blue is the
car controlled by our policy which got
lost because they already the other guy
got you know went to a different path so
our blue guy here has to survive this
jungle of other cars they cannot see us
right so in this case we are slightly
ahead slightly behind slightly we are
accelerating a lot and we survived in
the other case is well we are the blue
guy the yellow one is the original guy
in the in the data and oh we again
managed to diverge from the original
trajectory but we still survive until
the end and slides as we were mentioning
so okay this is like a summary of the
whole thing model predictive policy
learning with uncertainty repolarization
for driving during dense traffic you
should have understand everything now so
model prediction like okay and just you
have the four different points that are
uncertain in the regularizer letting
dropout large-scale data set and then
you have the additional cost for you
know trying to mimic the experts
information and these are the links for
everything so that's the title that's me
collaborators are well main authors we
are both first outers Micahel and myself
and then division slides are here the
article is here the code is available on
github on my github and this is a
website and we also have a poster sorry
it'll be running so so so late but I
hope you really enjoyed this small
project of ours there were so many
questions I didn't plan there is another
explanation of this there is another
explanation of this project on my
YouTube Israel is 20 minutes long maybe
I've done a better job than today but
maybe I did a better job today since I
was answering your questions so if there
are no other questions we gonna see each
other next week and again if someone can
help out with the review of last scribes
from the lab would be very helpful or
because I I have no idea how to deal
with this otherwise is the mall is a
word model frozen when training the
agent yeah as as we have seen last week
do we still have time for questions of
course any time since when you're
training the network since it's kind of
like a recurrent architecture are we
worried about like vanishing gradients
and how do you with with such a complex
model how do you like address that all
right so it's not that complex as in
this is two layer neural net so the
policy is very stupid policy like it's
very tiny the word model is a bit larger
but nevertheless we have batch norm
which is keep you know helping out
sending things through like the
gradients throw and then
I think we also used the Samsung
receiver connections because those are
units yeah so you know the gradients
didn't give us big issues for training
this model also we are doing 1330 times
steps in the future so it was like three
seconds in the future given that we
start from I think two seconds in the
past so we're always like five seconds
window temporal window for training the
system I didn't quite understand how the
when we're doing the latent dropout how
that works how that helps us with I
guess would you call it like like
disentangling the action versus the
latent right so the problem was here
right so the problem was that the fact
that we have access to the future if we
make a small tiny change in my steering
steering wheel control everything will
change which is a very large change
right and that MSC will to minimize that
MSE you know a lot of information will
go through that way because it's a big
change right so it's very is a brutal
change now and you know if that latent
variable that way little Bible will try
to to acknowledge the fact that
everything changes an 80 just changed
slightly right because it's just a tiny
change of the steering wheel the problem
is that if you're forward if your
predictive model on this is called
forward model is no longer looking at
what is the steering wheel then you know
you can steer around but the network
will not care about what is your control
may instead be you want to have a
network that if you steer to the left
he's gonna tell you everything steers to
the right by the fact that you steer to
the left so you had to disentangle this
and to fix that the thing that really
worked very well was this one which was
basically half of the time or maybe we
had some shading I forgot but you know
some some times instead of you know
sampling the latent variable
while training these automation of
encoder instead of sampling it all the
time from your encoder sometimes it's
just simple from the prior distribution
in this way rotation in the future
cannot be explained by the latent
variable therefore there must be a path
that connects the action to the future
state right so if you break this arrow
you have to break this arm if I do this
switching between this one and the other
you basically Blake you break this arrow
for you know a fraction of the
iterations and therefore the arrow will
not actually subsist because it cannot
use it right to make a prediction if
sometimes it happens sometimes it
doesn't happen the network always sees
this action right this action is gonna
be always turning left turn right that
are mystically determing the fact that
is steer to the left to the right this
is kind of a way to make the network
like see the action when it's performing
the training yeah this was a big issue
without these things it doesn't work
because you would have a network which
is not carrying at all something nice
you can do is gonna be like adversarial
adversarial something you want to want
to get a network which is gonna be
killing you like if the future changed
because of the action or not and it said
the prior distribution for the latent
variable is just like a Gaussian normal
okay all right cool thank you so much
Yan keeps saying that we sample from
zero that was the previous previous
version where we actually didn't even
have a variational encoder and we had
just a encoder which was encoding the
mean so we we didn't have the same thing
module we didn't have the variance just
we had an encoder which was just giving
me this latent so that was the previous
version no sampling no V you just F ank
you encode this guy and so sometimes you
were getting it from the encoder and
sometimes you were picking it from zero
because we trained this first branch
with this guy that was not here right so
we first trained this stuff
deterministically which is or is it here
so initially we trained these which
means set Z to 0 right so if you set the
Z to 0 there you go you get this back
deterministic so basically whenever you
do this dropouts trick you switch back
and forth between the deterministic and
the stochastic version of the predictive
model
kula sounds crazy I think well yeah I I
think you should be able to digest this
stuff because you're good you're good
students it might interest you more
questions yeah al yeah so I wanted I
just wanted to check my understanding of
latent variable models
it seems that different models use
latent variables for different
objectives like the auto encoder uses it
to learn a low dimensional
representation then we AE the
variational auto encoder builds on it to
regularize the latent space so that it
can randomly sample from the Nathan
space and then Gans and the model that
we just studied they use it to introduce
randomness so that when we have the same
input and different outcomes the network
doesn't have to output an average of the
predictions and so basically here we are
using latent space to provide more
dimension led to the input to introduce
randomness to the input so in this case
we have this latent variable to account
for what cannot be account from the past
array so the point is that you know not
everything is predictable and so if you
cannot predict everything you're gonna
make some errors so this latent variable
allow you to tune your algorithm to
actually you know zero out that error
and later on you can sample this latent
variable in order to get you know proper
predictions so without the laden bag
what you are getting that you know
masked version of the prediction it's
blurry prediction instead in order to
get you know Chris predictions you want
to refine your average prediction to the
specific case you have at hand right got
it so it is basically using it to add
dimensionality to the input to make
things more specific
I wouldn't say dimensionizer to the
import
I would say you add latent variables in
order to provide the missing information
that would be required for you to make a
proper prediction got it
good thank you of course more questions
I know it's so it's so late I'm taking
this was very extreme extremely lengthy
class I feel sorry more questions I
can't see you hold on stop share screen
okay
Oh 50 people still here okay what do you
want to know else I also want to check
my understanding for later was correct
so today tomorrow will tell us something
that we cannot predict from the future
but you just said if we turn lab
everything would be like to our right
but you don't want me to tell this
information you want this information
all it comes from our action yeah
exactly because if you if you if you
steer to their left everything will turn
to the right right if you if you're
riding a bicycle and you're doing like
that you're gonna go you exactly know
how you will evolve right you don't know
if you're gonna be crashing into someone
and that's gonna be taken care by the
latent variable and which is gonna be
you know patching your wrong prediction
due to unforeseen events but everything
that is you know predictable should be
done by the deterministic branch such
that you use the past information to
determine what's happening next
but then you can't really name so it's
like you know you're gonna be me trying
to touch the calm web web-cam here but
then there is some wind because I open
the window so I go here and it goes
there I go here and it goes here right
so if there is a additional component it
is like moving my hand I will have to
deal with that for the specific case so
I can only go here given that I know
that my finger will go forward from the
past to the future I
exactly nowhere to go but if there are
additional you know inputs that are not
under my control then you will not be
able to make accurate predictions unless
you have some knowledge it's like okay
like going back to the example yan makes
all the time with a pencil right so the
pen is gonna be falling one direction
let me get the pens
get the pen if you let it go it's gonna
be falling in one direction goes another
direction goes the third direction right
so you can first learn you know massive
Network which is learning the dynamics
of falling right so you learn how a pen
falls down the only little information
you know - you need to know that you
can't know in advance is in which
direction it will fall so you're gonna
have the big ass Network learning the
folding dynamics and then the last
minimal amount of information that is
missing is in which direction you should
actually you know initiate this folding
trajectory right so this is how it works
bid network to learn the big bulk of
prediction little tiny little variable
right so this latent variable again I
said is something like 16 dimensions
it's very tiny like a very short vector
which is just providing you the missing
information to make a sharp prediction
okay okay so to avoid the latent
variable to tell us information that
should be predictable we are trying to
approach the regularization term the KO
term from with the help of prior okay so
yes so the KL term it's necessary for
you otherwise things will explode as we
have seen in class right if you don't
have the KL this prediction will go as
far as possible because they don't want
to overlap the second term is going to
be the actual network will try to
collapse them right so whenever you
introduce this KL you enforce the bubble
to be having variants of one and also
all the mean to be close to zero such
that you feel that you know
fear with little bubbles and then later
on given that now all these fears are
within this bubble you can simple from
you know a Gaussian distribution like a
normal distribution from the same size
so that's why we use the KL the part
that allows you to be you know if you if
you have like if you put a lot of
strength on the KL you are going to be
also reducing the amount of information
so you can use that KL as a term to
reduce the amount of information coming
from the future so that's definitely one
way of regularizing the the latent
variable the other way is also the other
the other trick we are using is the drop
out streak for the latent which is
sometimes you know sampling completely
from the prior and such that now the
backbone the the big massive network the
deterministic one cannot rely on
information it is you know not always
present right okay and all this happen
in the training stage of the predictive
model yeah okay okay yeah thank you
thank you so much yeah yeah could you so
regarding that forward model uncertainty
is that uncertainty that comes from like
trying to predict more in the future or
so the uncertainty there I I think I
went a little faster the uncertainty
coming there is the fact that you know
whenever you have your policy
trying to control the other guy you can
you know press a lot the acceleration or
you can you know steer completely like
crazy
and if you give yeah you know some
actions that are far from the training
domain of that policy different policies
will reply will will respond in a
different way right because if you train
several models on the same training data
and then you test this multiple models
train on this data outside
the training interval let's say let's
say this is oh I cannot speak with a pen
in the mouth interval right and then we
had the you know a your test on our
fryer here right so if you in this
training interval here all the model
will agree and therefore the variance
across this training interval will be
very tiny as you go away from the
training interval the variance will
increase right the nice part is now that
given that this variance is you know
it's a scalar value you can minimize the
variance by having the action going from
clear draw here because here the
variance is tiny
right the variance here is minimum and
here the variance is very large so you
can have actions that might great in
your action space such that the variance
is minimized right so your variance now
is your loss you do gradient descent in
action space for variance minimization
and therefore you can travel no in this
action space which actually is to the
arc is actually two dimensional right
it's so cool so you have you know X
Direction y direction you have the day
the hill in this case you can plot the
variance right so if the variance goes
up here you can go in the center down
such that in this region where the
variance is low you know that all these
different models will agree for the
future predictions therefore and those
actions are coming from you know safe
Riaan right the actions are now coming
from more like the training points
rather than outside point a training
region let's say this way yeah right
okay thank you
of course more questions ask me
everything
Emma Emma how do you say MEA all right
mark
you're done am I gonna be cooking dinner
I have one question
so suppose we change the context of this
problem from regression to some
classification problem for example water
predict are we going to crash or not or
if you want to predict is there high
traffic or not then will the
effectiveness of latent variables still
be present
like would latent variables improve the
model even if it were a classification
setting and more because both from what
I've observed it seems like latent
variables always improve the performance
in like a generation when we want to
generate something like in generate an
image or a music synthesis or some
regression prediction but in a
classification setting how effective
will they be so we are actually working
on this right now we are working on
classification
and maybe we can hear about more about
this next week when we're going to be
talking about language this is actually
was another student of Leon is working
on using latent variable models for
performing classification that allows
you to pick for multiple multiple
options so I guess you're gonna hear
about this one
not not today
or you can ask yuan next time but again
we're gonna be I think we make it we can
mention this next week
okay thanks all right
that's it all right have a good night
have enjoy your meal I stay safe wash
your hands and the pen I don't was not
sanitized but I haven't used it so good
point
don't touch your face don't on stay safe
why
[Music]
how can you get more out of this course
right overall so let me give you a few
suggestions first comprehension if
something was still not clear just ask
me the question a section below the
video I will answer every question so
you will get it eventually if you'd like
to I get more news about the field
things I do on in terms of educational
content and things I find interesting
you can follow up on Twitter and there
you have my handle I've seen that if
you'd like to have updates about newer
videos don't forget to subscribe to the
channel and activate the notification
bell if you actually like this video
don't forget to put a thumbs up it helps
as well recommending this video to other
people if you'd like to search the
content of this lesson we have our
English transcription which is connected
directly to this video so every title in
the transcription is clickable if you
click on the title you get the right
director to the correct location on the
video in the same way each section of
the video is the same title is in
transcription so you can go back and
forth maybe English is not your first
language but l'italiano habla espanol
new Obama speak Korean have no idea how
to speak Korean well we have several
translations of this material available
on at the website so and we are also
looking for more translations if you can
help as well it's really important that
you actually try to do some of the
exercises and you play around with the
notebooks and the source code we
provided in order to internalize and
understand better the concepts we
explained during the lessons contribute
this is really giving you the
opportunity to show your contribution
for example you find some typos in the
write-up so you find some bugs in the
notebooks you can fix those and you know
be part of this whole project by sending
me a poor request on github or letting
me know otherwise and that was it so see
you next time bye bye